A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
Library of Virginia
79 volume; .45 cubic feet (1 box).
Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Augusta County in 2008 under the accession numbers 43658 and 43836.
Alternative Form Available
John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247
Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 253, 255, 256
Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244
Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 248, 254, 255
Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 249
Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 247
Mictiow Sales Book, 183 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 255
Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 249, 250
Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 247, 253
Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 244
Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reel 257
Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875 is available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 244-245, 256-257
William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826 are available as microfilm Augusta County (Va.) Reels 246, 252, 253
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Augusta County was named for Augusta of Saxe-Gotha, who married Frederick Louis, Prince of Wales, and was the mother of King George III. It was formed from Orange County by a statute of 1738 that stipulated that when the population was large enough the new county government would begin to function. The county court first met on 9 December 1745.
Scope and Content
Augusta County (Va.) Business Records,1789-1908, is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies is pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Augusta County (Va.). Represented records largely consists of bound volumes such as ledgers, daybooks, minute books, cashbooks, invoice books, and account books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861
Series II: John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842
Series III: Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907
Series IV: John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837
Series V: John Frazier and Bath and Rockbridge Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854
Series VI: Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867
Series VII: Henry Holloway Plantation Ledger, 1796-1810
Series VIII: Houff & Holler Business Records, 1904-1908
Series IX: Breeze Johnson Ledger, 1839-1847
Series X: Nicholas C. Kinney Daybook and Ledgers, 1815-1830
Series XI: Mandelbaum Clothier Daybook, 1871
Series XII: Mercer Salt Works Business Records, 1851-1856
Series XIII: Mictiow Sales Book, 1837
Series XIV: Mount Ery Furnace Ledger, 1789-1793
Series XV: Mutual Annuity Company Ledger, 1892-1906
Series XVI: Timothy M. Patterson General Store Ledgers, 1792-1805
Series XVII: Tannehill & Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874
Series XVIII: Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831
Series XIX: Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860
Series XX: Thornburg and Shafer Daybook, 1877-1879
Series XXI: Unidentified General Store Daybooks, 1828-1835
Series XXII: Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873
Series XXIII: Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875
Series XXIV:Virginia Express Company Minute Book and Cashbook, 1867-1869
Series XXV: John Wayt Invoice Book, 1828-1831
Series XXVI:William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: August County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912
Additional August County(Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Based out of Hartford, Connecticut, the Aetna Insurance Company sold its first life insurance policy in 1850. In 1853, the company was incorporated as the Aetna Life Insurance Company with former Connecticut judge Eliphalet A. Bulkeley as its first president. In 1861, the company began offering participating life insurance policies, and at the end of the Civil War, Aetna was one of the nation's biggest life insurance providers. Today, Aetna is a diversified health care benefits company providing a range of health care insurance products and related services including dental, pharmacy, group life, and disability insurance.
  Aetna Insurance Company established an insurance agency in Staunton, Virginia, in the mid-nineteenth century. Alexander F. Kinney served as an agent for the company. Kinney, a Virginia resident born about 1836, was also a bank teller and a circuit court clerk for Augusta County.
  Scope and Content: Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers, 1857-1861, record the disbursements of the company for such expenses as advertising, express or freight charges, taxes, return premiums, etc. All vouchers were signed by Aetna's agent Alexander F. Kinney.
  - Aetna Insurance Company Vouchers 1857-1861
- John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842, 1 volume
  Historical Information: John Armstrong, Sr. was a farmer in Augusta County, Virginia. He had a son, John Armstrong, Jr., who owned a neighboring farm. He died in 1842.
  Scope and Content: John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger, 1827-1842, records Armstrong's personal finances along with the business activities of his farm. Each account records the transactions with individuals that Armstrong either hired or with whom he conducted business. Information found in each entry include the date, type of transaction, and monies debited or credited to the account. Armstrong recorded purchases for such items as wheat, bacon, brandy, tallow, butter, dry apples, and flour. There are also larger purchases such as livestock and furniture. In addition, Armstrong recorded the work done by white laborers which included such tasks as sawing wood, mowing, etc.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Admr. of John Armstrong, Sr. vs Admr. of John Armstrong, Jr., Etc.1860-074. Avaible Digitially through the Chancery Records Index.
  - John Armstrong, Sr. Ledger 1827-1842
- Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907 1885-1907, 20 volumes
  Historical Information: The Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company financed loans for land purchases and building constructions in Augusta County, Va. The company was formed on 7 February 1885 at a meeting conducted at the city clerks office in Staunton, Va., by a group of citizens wishing to organize a building and loan association. Early officers of the company included M. Erskine Miller, president; John W. Stout, vice president; and Newton Argenbright, secretary. Later presidents included A. C. Gordon and J. N. McFarland. The company suspended operations and began a long process of voluntary liquidation in December of 1898.
  Scope and Content: The Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Business Records, 1885-1907, consists of three daybooks, five cashbooks, four letter books, two ledgers, one index, one minute book, one statement book, two Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books, and one stock receipt book.
  - Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books 1885-1906, 2 volumes
    Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Books,1885-1906, were used to record both the money owed by the building and loan company and the money owed to the company by customers and shareholders. Both of the account books contain two separate halves -- one for bills payable and the other for bills receivable. Each entry includes the date, name of the customer or shareholder, and the bank where the payments were made. For bills payable, the company which is owed money to is noted along with the name of the building and loan employee responsible for the transaction. Some entries note that full statements of the accounts can be found in the accompanying letter books.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Co. Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Book, 1885-1906
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Co. Bills Payable and Bills Receivable Account Book, 1887-1895
  - Cashbooks, 1885-1907, 5 volumes
    Cashbooks, 1885-1907, record cash received and cash disbursed. Transactions are listed chronologically as they occurred. Entries document monies credited and debited for such activities as bills received, costs of sales,and interest paid on accounts. Other entries track monies received and dispersed on individual accounts for dues and running shares, loans, interest, fines, and stock transfers. Company expenses were recorded for items such as employee salaries, taxes paid, rent, commissioners' fees, insurance premiums, attorney fees, advertising, and postage.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book, 1885-1887 1885-1887
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book, 1887-1888
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cashbook, 1888-1893
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cashbook, 1894-1902
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Cash Book, 1902-1907
  - Daybooks, 1885-1906, 3 volumes
    Daybooks, 1885- 1906, document business activities on a chronological basis as they occurred. Entries include date, account name, type of transaction, and monies credited and debited. Transactions recorded include real estate loans, costs of sales, stock values and stock purchases, interest due on individual accounts, profits and loss statements, and expenses such as insurance, taxes, and fines. Records of stock purchases contain the name of buyer, the dollar amount of stock purchased, and the entrance fees applied to the purchase.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building & Loan Company Daybook, 1885-1890
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Daybook, 1890-1897
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Day Book, 1897-1906
  - Ledgers, 1885-1907, 2 volumes
    Ledger, 1889-1898, records the accounts of "holders of paid up stock." Each entry includes the date, number of stock shares bought or sold, and the amounts debited or credited to the account. If stock shares were recorded as sold, the name of the buyer was listed in the transaction.
    Ledger A, 1885-1907, records the accounts of individual stockholders and individual loan holders. Information found in the accounts of individual stockholders include the date of transaction and the amounts of stock purchased. Transactions in the accounts of individual loan holders document the loan purchase amount, interest fees, and fines. Payments on the accounts were also recorded and were made either with cash or redeemed stock. Some accounts include notations of actions taken on the account such as paid in full, case in litigation, or property sold at auction. The back of the ledger includes a totaling of representative accounts such as bills receivable, capital stock, subscribed stock, redeemed stock, expenses, and cash accounts. Account entries concerning stock include the name of the purchaser along with the amount of stock purchased.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Ledger A, 1885-1907
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Index to Loans and General Accounts, 1885-1907
      Provides an index to the individual accounts found in Ledger A
    - Augusta Perpetual Building & Loan Company Ledger, 1889-1898
  - Letter books, 1886-1902, 4 volumes
    Letter Books, 1886-1902, provide a record of out-going correspondence related to the company's business activities. Letter topics include requests for account balances to be paid, demands for the sale of land or property to settle a debt, and details of monies received and owed on individual accounts. The majority of the letters are signed by W. T. McCue, who was identified as the cashier for the company; however a few were signed by Taylor Bissell, a clerk for the company.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book, 1886-1891
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book, 1891-1895
    - Augusta Perpetual Building & Loan Company Letter Book, 1895-1900
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Letter Book, 1900-1902
  - Minute books, 1885-1903, 1 volume
    Records the meetings of the company's board of directors and meetings of the stockholders. Early entries in February of 1885 document the formation of the building and loan association and the creation of a constitution and by-laws for the government of the company. These early meetings also established stock prices and membership fees and elected officers and committee members. Business statements for the company were presented to the board of directors on a semi-annual basis. These statements documented the profits and loses of the company and documented such items as stock subscriptions, loans on real estate, stock dues, bills receivable, bills payable, loss and gain records, and company resources and liabilities. Applications to redeem stock and applications for loans on real estate were presented for approval at meetings. Because the company's constitution stipulated that "stockholders must be a white person," several meetings discussed the "legal right of the association to make loans to colored people through the intervention of a white applicant." It was ultimately decided that to protect the company both the white applicant and the colored borrower should execute the bond for loans. In December of 1898, a resolution was recommended to stockholders that the company suspend operations as a building and loan company and that it was in the best interest of the company to go into voluntary liquidation, collect the company's assets, and return money to stockholders. Meetings held from 1899 to 1903 concern the liquidation of the business.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building & Loan Company Board of Directors Minute Book, 1885-1903
  - Statement books, 1886-1898, 1 volume
    Records the financial statements of the company at the end of each fiscal year beginning in December of 1886. The statement book was used by the committee appointed by the Board of Directors to examine the company's books and papers. The business statements document stock accounts, loans, interest due and unpaid on accounts, and fines unpaid for each fiscal year. The stock accounts and loan account statements include the name of the individual shareholder, the number of shares bought or sold, and the monies debited or credited to the accounts. For each fiscal year, balance sheets provide the company's profits and loss statements and include a list of resources (loans, bills receivable, cash, property) and liabilities (stock dues, bills payable).
    - Augusta Perpetual Building and Loan Company Statement Book, 1886-1898
  - Stock Reciept books, 1889-1898, 1 volume
    Includes duplicate stock certificates kept for the company's records of stock shares purchased. Each stock certificate includes a certificate number, date, name of buyer, and the number of shares purchased.
    - Augusta Perpetual Building & Loan Company Stock Receipt Book, 1889-1898
- John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837, 1 volume
  Historical Information: John B. Christian was a merchant in Augusta County, Virginia, in the early nineteenth century. Christian dealt primarily in the grocery and grain trades selling items such as wheat, corn, sugar, and coffee.
  Scope and Content: John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837, records the accounts of individual customers. Each customer account includes separate entries for purchases and payments made. Purchases were not detailed but rather include the prices per unit and the total purchase price made for that day. However, details were provided for payments made toward account balances. John B. Christian accepted cash, bartered items (whiskey, butter, livestock, hats, etc.), and labor (hauling, carpentry work, etc.) as payments. Beginning in 1829, customer accounts include the items purchased. Examples of items purchased include flour, bran, wheat, corn, rye, beef, sugar, and coffee. In addition to the customer accounts, the back of the volume was used to record the number and weights of hogs butchered.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Anthony Beard vs. Heirs of John B. Christian 1842-027. Avaible Digitially through the Chancery Records Index.
  - John B. Christian Ledger, 1817-1837
- John Frazier and Bath and Rockbridge Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854, 1 volume
  Historical Information: John W. Frazier, born about 1810, was a farm and hotelkeeper in Bath County and Rockbridge County, Virginia. Frazier owned and operated two mineral springs resorts, Bath Alum Spring and Rockbridge Alum Spring. Frazier purchased the Rockbridge Alum Spring property, a noted antebellum spa complex, in 1852. Frazier began building on the property in 1852 but died in 1853 before the building project was completed. Frazier's brother William Frazier oversaw the completion of the project, and the final results consisted of a large central hotel building flanked with cottages and supporting service buildings. The resort included a barroom and a building used as a store and post office. The hotel property was converted into a hospital in 1861. After the Civil War, an attempt to revive the spa resort failed and the property was ultimately sold at auction in 1880. Today what remains of the old spa property is owned by the Young Life organization.
  Scope and Content: John W. Frazier and Bath and Rockbridge Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854, records the financial activities of Frazier and his hotels, two of which were the Bath Alum Spring and the Rockbridge Alum Spring. The ledger documents the accounts of individual customers and employees. Each entry includes the date, type of transaction, and monies credited and debited to the accounts. The early part of the ledger pertains to the accounts of John Frazier's store customers. Customers purchased such items as butter, meal, eggs, sugar, coffee, tobacco, and bacon. Beginning in 1852, the ledger was used to record the business activities of the two alum springs resorts. For Bath Alum Spring, customer accounts document purchases made at the Fairview Store, which sold items such as whiskey, tobacco, sugar, coffee, and cloth. Beginning in 1852, Frazier made entries pertaining to the building project at Rockbridge Alum Spring. Employee accounts document blacksmith work and the buying and hauling of lumber and other building supplies. Also in 1852, customer accounts for hotel customers begin to appear. Transactions document lodging expenses, tavern bills, meals purchased, and livery fees.
  Recorded throughout the ledger are entries pertaining to the hire of enslaved individuals. One such entry, mentions the arrival of Alfred Tyler and Rachel and brother. The remainder of these entries merely include the prices paid for the ensalved individuals hired.
  In 1853, the ledger was used by William Frazier who took control of John W. Frazier's estate after his death. William Frazier primarily used the ledger to document the settlement of outstanding accounts. Located in the back of the ledger is a detailed listing of inventory on hand at the Fairview Store in 1854. Examples of items in the inventory include china, glassware, spices, medicines, hardware items, and cloth.
  - John Frazier & Alum Springs Ledger, 1850-1854
- Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers and Daybook, 1839-1867, 5 volumes
  Historical Information: Alanson Harris, born in 1812, owned a blacksmith business in Augusta County (Va.). Harris often performed carpentry work with the assistance of carpenter E. B. Simpson. Simpson, born in 1832, lived in Augusta County (Va.) until he relocated to Colorado in the 1870s.
  Scope and Content: Alanson Harris Blacksmith business records, 1839-1867, consist of three ledgers, one blacksmith and carpentry work ledger, and one daybook.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Creditors of Alanson Harris vs Administrator of Alanson Harris, 1890-060. Avaible Digitially through the Chancery Records Index.
  - Alanson Harris Blacksmith and Carpentry Work Ledger, 1860-1867
    Blacksmith and Carpentry Work Ledger, 1860-1867, records the carpentry work performed for individual customers. Information found in each account includes the date; amounts of shingles, posts, planks, or timber sawed; and the monies debited or credited to the customer's account. A majority of the carpentry work was done with the assistance of carpenter E. B. Simpson.
  - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Daybook, 1856
    Daybook, 1856, records work performed on almost a daily basis. Each entry includes customer name, service provided, and the amount charged for the service. Examples of work performed include shoeing horses, repairing tools, and some carpentry work such as making coffins. The daybook was also used to record the amount of wood hauled throughout the year. These transactions include the customer name and the monies received.
  - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledger, 1839-1866
    Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledger, 1839-1866, records the accounts of individual customers. Each account entry lists transactions in chronological order and includes the amounts owed and paid. The ledger is separated into two parts, each of which has its own index. The first half of the ledger, 1839-1840, could pertain to the business M. G. & Co., which is embossed on the spine of the ledger. There is no mention of this business within the ledger, but there are several references to members of the Harris family, specifically George T. Harris and Frank L. Harris. Entries are listed in chronological order under individual account names with amounts owed and paid, and each transaction is described as being for either merchandise, sundries, or interest. The second half of the ledger, 1864-1866, is devoted to the blacksmith business operated by Alanson Harris. Transactions, listed under individual account names, record activities such as shoeing horses, making nails, sharpening knives and shears, repairing wagons and carriages, and repairing mill and farm equipment such as reapers and plows.
  - Alanson Harris Blacksmith Ledgers, 1860-1862; 1860-1867